<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A short information, but agreeable vnto Scripture: of idol-images· Made vnto the Christian congregation at Prague, when as, by his Royall Maiesties most gracious command, the Castle-church there, was clensed from all images, on Sonday the twelfth of December, in the yeare 1619. By Abraham Scultetus. Faithfully translated according to the high Dutch copie printed at Heidelberge, by Gotthard Vœgeliu, 1620.</title>
            <author>Scultetus, Abraham, 1566-1624.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1620</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 33 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11828</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 22126</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S121082</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99856271</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99856271</idno>
            <idno type="VID">21800</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11828)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21800)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1257:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A short information, but agreeable vnto Scripture: of idol-images· Made vnto the Christian congregation at Prague, when as, by his Royall Maiesties most gracious command, the Castle-church there, was clensed from all images, on Sonday the twelfth of December, in the yeare 1619. By Abraham Scultetus. Faithfully translated according to the high Dutch copie printed at Heidelberge, by Gotthard Vœgeliu, 1620.</title>
                  <author>Scultetus, Abraham, 1566-1624.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[30] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>S.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M.D.C.XX. [1620]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>German original not traced.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication conjectured by STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: [A]⁴ (-[A]1) B-D⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Idols and images --  Worship --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Reformation --  Czech Republic --  Prague --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:21800:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21800:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> A Short Information, but agreeable vnto Scripture: OF IDOL-IMAGES.</p>
            <p>Made vnto the Chriſtian Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation at <hi>Prague,</hi> when as, by his Royall Maieſties moſt gracious Command, the <hi>Caſtle-Church there, was clenſed from all</hi> Images, on Sonday the twelfth of <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cember,</hi> in the yeare 1619.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Abraham Scultetus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Faithfully tranſlated according to the <hi>high Dutch</hi> Copie printed at <hi>Heidelberge,</hi> by <hi>Gotthard Voege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liu,</hi> 1620.</p>
            <p>M. D. C. XX.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:21800:2"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="entrance">
            <pb facs="tcp:21800:2"/>
            <head>The Entrance.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Doubt not but that there are many, who will thinke it ſtrange, which either now do ſee and behold, or ſhortly ſhall heare and vnderſtand, that the Altar and Images are remooued and put out of this Church. For many men will perhaps thus thinke and ſay with themſelues: That God might euen as well haue bin ſerued and honored through the Images: That alſo they were the common peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples Bookes and Bible: And that the Altar and Images did much adorne and beautifie the Church, which now (being diſpoyled of theſe Ornaments) ſeemes to bee bare and naked like a Wilderneſſe.</p>
            <p>Now therefore the better to meet with, and ſatisfie ſuch conceited thoughts, I will for this time lay aſide and pretermit the Text of the Goſpell appointed for this day; and briefly, yet plainly and euidently declare vnto you, what al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty Gods will and pleaſure is, concerning ſuch Images and Altars. Which will and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of God, when it ſhall be brought forth, and made manifeſt out of the holy Scripture, as cleere as the day light and bright Sun-ſhine, then ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:21800:3"/> not any bee iuſtly offended, at the clenſing and purging of this Church from Images. But all godly minded people that doe ſee it, or ſhall heare of it, will ſpiritually much reioyce thereat, and be heartily thankefull for the ſame, firſt vnto the moſt high God, &amp; next vnto his royal Maieſty.</p>
            <p>Wherefore that all may become profitable vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs, we will firſt call vpon our Lord God, for the grace and aſsiſtance of his holy Spirit, with the ſame prayer which our Lord and Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt himſelfe hath taught vs, ſaying, <hi>Our Father, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="Scripture_passage">
               <head>The Text.</head>
               <q>
                  <hi>Thus ſpake the ſtrong and iealous God, out of the fire vnto the people of Iſrael:</hi>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>EXOD.</hi> 20. 4, 5, 6.</bibl> Thou ſhalt not make vnto thee any grauen Image, or any likeneſſe of any thing that is in Heauen aboue, or that is in the Earth beneath, or that is in the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter vnder the Earth. Thou ſhalt not bow downe thy ſelfe to them, nor ſerue them: For I the LORD thy God am a iealous God, viſiting the iniquitie of the fathers vpon the children vnto the third and fourth generation of them that hate mee: And ſhewing mercy vnto thouſands of them that loue mee, and keepe my Commandements.</q>
            </div>
            <div type="exposition">
               <head>The Expoſition.</head>
               <p>ANd if <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> ſtood here together, yet could they not ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly vtter, with what
<pb facs="tcp:21800:3"/> a fiery zeale the Lord God hath forbidden, to make &amp; worſhip Images. For when the Lord gaue the ten Commandements, he threatned not in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Commandement ſo hard and grieuous a pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment vnto the tranſgreſſors; and promiſed not in any Commandement vnto the obedient perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers, ſo large a bleſſing, as in the Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Images. For hee will puniſh thoſe who tranſgreſſe this Commandement, euen vnto the fourth generation; but will richly and ouer-abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly reward thoſe with grace and mercy, who obediently obſerue and keepe this Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p>And the Lord God hath not repeated any Commandement ſo often, as hee hath done euen this Commandement of Images. For in the twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieth Chapter of <hi>Exodus,</hi> when hee firſt gaue the ten Commandements, he doth not therupon pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently repeat any other Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandement, then this, and ſaith: <hi>Ye haue ſeene that I haue talked with you</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Exod.</hi> 22. 22, 23.</note> 
                  <hi>from Heauen. Therefore yee ſhall not make with me</hi> (any thing) <hi>Gods of Siluer, neither ſhall ye make vnto you Gods of Gold.</hi> And when <hi>Moſes</hi> was ready to dye, &amp; admoniſheth the people of their dutie, he preſſeth not any Inhibition ſo deeply in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their hearts, as euen that Inhibition of Images. For in the fourth Chapter of <hi>Deuteronomie,</hi> he thus ſpeaketh vnto the people: <hi>Take ye therefore</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Deut.</hi> 4. 15, 16, 17, 18.</note> 
                  <hi>good heed vnto your ſelues. (For ye ſaw no manner of ſimilitude on the day that the Lord ſpake vnto you in Horeb, out of the fire.) Lest ye corrupt your ſelues, and</hi>
                  <gap reason="missing" extent="1+ pages">
                     <desc>〈1… pages missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:21800:4"/> cording to his Eſſence and being: But yet he may bee grauen and pictured according to that forme, wherein he appeared vnto diuers of the faithfull in the old Teſtament.</p>
               <p>To which I anſwere: God may at his pleaſure, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
                  </label> appeare in what forme or ſhape he will; but yet it becommeth vs to follow his Commandement: <hi>Thou ſhalt not make vnto thee any Image.</hi> Againe, <hi>Make not vnto you any Image, the likeneſſe of any fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure.</hi> Beſides, the formes and ſhapes wherein the Lord God did at any time appeare vnto any of the Saints, were not in any wiſe Gods Image and Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture. For God onely tooke ſuch formes &amp; ſhapes vpon him but for a time, and did ſoone after, lay them aſide againe. And thus did he alſo ſhew and reueale himſelfe, ſometimes now preſently after this forme, then anon againe, after another forme; in ſo much that a man muſt needs ſtand in doubt, which forme and ſhape was Gods true likeneſſe and ſimilitude. Therefore the Prophet <hi>Eſay,</hi> not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding he had ſeene the Lord ſit on the Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eſay</hi> 40. 22, 25.</note> of the Earth, euen aboue on high, as vpon an eleuated ſeat, whoſe clothing filled the Temple; yet doth he reprooue all them who will make any Image, likeneſſe, or ſimilitude of God, and asketh as was heard, ſaying: <hi>To whom then will ye liken me?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>3. So alſo God ſhould not, nor ought to bee <note place="margin">3. God ſhould not, nor ought to be pictured.</note> grauen or pictured. For ſuch Imagery is both hurt full vnto men, and diſhonourable vnto God. It is hurtfull vnto men; for a man may ſoone thereby corrupt and vndoe himſelfe, yea, and prouoke the
<pb facs="tcp:21800:4"/> Lord God vnto anger againſt him, as it is written in the fore-alleaged fourth of <hi>Deuteronomy.</hi> It is diſhonorable, and a diſparagement vnto the Lord God, as whoſe Glory and Maieſty cannot by any meanes be grauen or pictured, with any manner of viſible Image or Picture. Whence it is, that the holy Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> writes in the firſt Chapter to the <hi>Romanes, That the Heathen became Fooles,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ro.</hi> 1. 22, 23.</note> 
                  <hi>when they changed the glory of the vncorruptible God, into an Image made like to corruptible man, &amp; birds, and to foure footed beaſts, &amp; creeping things.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This doctrine of ours concerning the forbidden Images and Pictures of God, is ſo cleere and eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, that it is alſo acknowledged of ſundry prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal Popiſh Diuines, to be ſound, good, and agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the will of God. For one of them called <hi>Gabriel Vaſquetz,</hi> acknowledgeth plainly, ſpeaking <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lib.</hi> 2. <hi>de a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorat. diſp.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 2.</note> of adoration; that all manner of picturing of God, is directly forbidden in the ſecond Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. And the chiefe <hi>Sorbon</hi> Doctors at <hi>Paris, Claudius Eſpencaeus, Salignacus, Picherellus,</hi> as as alſo with them Biſhop <hi>Monlucius</hi> haue long ſince ſhewed (as is to bee ſeene in the Hiſtory of the Reformed Churches in France the fourth Booke) that they therefore wiſhed, that all Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and Pictures of the holy Trinitie, were cleane remoued and wholly put out of Churches and Houſes, ſeeing the ſame are plainly forbidden by the Holy Scripture, by Councels, and by many godly, learned, and much prayſed worthy men.</p>
               <p>But yet here, mee thinkes, I heare ſome man ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>
                  </label>
                  <pb facs="tcp:21800:5"/> againe and demand: Seeing that the Sonne of God is become man, whether he may not be pic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tured according to his humanity?</p>
               <p>To which I anſwere: Chriſt came not therefore <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
                  </label> into the World, that men might take his Picture; but that men ſhould beleeue in him, and conuert themſelues vnto him. And therefore is it, that we haue not any Commandement at all, to make any ſuch Image or Picture, nor yet haue any example thereof in all the whole new Teſtament. As alſo he cannot poſſibly at this day be truly pictured, no not according to his humanitie, ſeeing there liues not now any man on the Earth that hath ſeene him. And heere hence it is, that one doth paint him with a yellowiſh, another with a flaxen, a third with a black, the fourth with a brown beard. And ſo then a man muſt take that for Chriſt his Picture, which the Painter holds in his opinion to be the beſt. Not to ſay any thing, that ſeeing Chriſt being true God and man, is in one perſon, they who boaſt to haue his Image and Picture, haue thereof notwithſtanding but a falſe Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Now as concerning the Images and Pictures of <note place="margin">Of the Images of Saints.</note> the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> of <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> and of other ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Saints: If a man knew of what forme and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion they properly were indeed, their Pictures might well be had in priuate houſes. But they are not by any meanes to be there ſet vp in thoſe pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, where men performe Gods publique ſeruice and worſhip, neither to bee prayed vnto, no nor yet for ornament ſake. Not to bee prayed vnto,
<pb facs="tcp:21800:5"/> that being a chiefe part of Gods worſhip. For it is written: <hi>Thou ſhalt not bow downe thy ſelfe vnto</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Exod.</hi> 20. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>them, nor ſerue them.</hi> And againe, <hi>Thou ſhalt wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 4. 10.</note> 
                  <hi>the Lord thy God, and him onely ſhalt thou ſerue,</hi> which is taken from the Law in <hi>Deuterono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Deut.</hi> 6. 3. <hi>&amp;</hi> 10. 20.</note> where the word <hi>(onely)</hi> is wanting, and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed by Chriſt as being Gods true meaning. Not for ornament ſake; for it is written: <hi>Abſtaine</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5. 22</note> 
                  <hi>from all appearance of euill.</hi> Now the Images ſet vpin holy places, haue the appearance of being prayed vnto and worſhipped: For there are many people who thinke and are perſwaded, they are ſet vp there for that very end &amp; purpoſe. And if they had not that appearance, yet there is great danger therein, that they may be prayed vnto, and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped of ſuperſtitious people: as we haue hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto ſeene, that it hath beene but too much prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed in this place. And we ought, as much as in vs lyeth, indeuour to auoyd and preuent ſuch danger. For it is written: <hi>Thou ſhalt not put a ſtumbling</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Leuit.</hi> 19. 14</note> 
                  <hi>block before the blind, but thou ſhalt feare thy God,</hi> ſaith the Lord in <hi>Leuiticus.</hi> And againe, Chriſt <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 4. 7.</note> ſaith, (out of <hi>Deut.</hi> 6. 16.) <hi>Thou ſhalt not tempt the Lord thy God.</hi> Wherefore the conſequent follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not, nor is of any value: It is lawfull to haue the Pictures of the Apoſtles, and of other holy Saints of God in priuate houſes: Therefore it is alſo lawfull to haue and ſet them vp publikely in Churches. For in a priuate houſe, (where the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants bee not ſuperſtitious) there is no appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of praying vnto them, and worſhipping of
<pb facs="tcp:21800:6"/> them, nor yet of any danger that they might bee prayed vnto, and worſhipped of other ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous people, and therefore are not there vnlawfull. And ſo much ſhall ſuffice to haue ſpoken of the firſt maine point; namely, that God ſhould not nor ought not, that God cannot bee grauen or pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctured.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the ſecond.</head>
               <p>But yet there are people here found, who giue <note place="margin">2. God will not be called vpon or honoured by Images.</note> out, that it is true indeed, men ſhould not pray, nor giue reuerence or worſhip vnto the Images &amp; Pictures; yea, and that they themſelues alſo doe it not. But yet ſay, that men may honour and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip God by and through the Pictures, according as theſe wordes following, ſtood written here on the beame vnder the great <hi>Crucifix:</hi>
               </p>
               <q xml:lang="lat">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Effigiem Chriſti, cùm tranſis ſemper honora:</l>
                     <l>Non tamen effigiem, ſed quem deſignat adora.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
               <p>That is:</p>
               <q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>When ere thou do'ſt before Chriſts Image ſtand,</l>
                     <l>Or paſſe it by; giue honour out of hand:</l>
                     <l>Yet not to th' Image, which thine eyes doe ſee;</l>
                     <l>But to the Lord it repreſents to thee.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
               <p>Whereunto we giue this anſwere: That it were much to be deſired, that Images were not indeed prayed vnto, and worſhipped at all. But the prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice and experience teacheth far otherwiſe: whilſt it is daily ſeene, how the people doe come, and bow themſelues before the Altars, Images and
<pb facs="tcp:21800:6"/> 
                  <hi>Crucifixes;</hi> how they put off their Hats vnto them; how they kindle Lamps and Tapers vnto them. And ſhould many of them ſee, that a <hi>Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſix</hi> ſhould bee hewed in pieces, or burned into aſhes, oh! how would euen their very heart then bleed for giefe? This is indeed truly to doe reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence and honour vnto Images, and make Idols of them. But goe too: Say, they pray not vnto the Images; ſay, they giue no reuerence, nor doe ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and worſhip vnto them. Yet will not God haue, nor can endure, that we pray vnto him, that we worſhip him, and that we giue him honour in, by, or through Images. For hee ſaith at once roundly and expreſly out: They ſhall not bee bowed downe vnto, nor ſerued. In which words he forbids all manner of ſeruice, honour, or wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, that may any way whatſoeuer be giuen vnto Images. As alſo it is written, <hi>Iohn</hi> 14. 6. that <hi>No man can come to the Father but by the Sonne:</hi> not by Images &amp; ſenceleſſe dumbe Idols. Beſides, it excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth not their Idolatry at all, that they pretend &amp; ſay; that through and by the Image, they pray vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to and call vpon the Sauiour. For the Iſraelites would not be taken or thought to pray vnto, and worſhip the golden Calfe: as they themſelues al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo ſay, <hi>To morrow is a Feaſt</hi> (not vnto the Calf, but) <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Exod.</hi> 32. 5, 8, 10.</note> 
                  <hi>vnto the Lord.</hi> And yet neuertheleſſe the Lord ſaith vnto <hi>Moſes, They haue worſhipped the Calfe, and haue ſacrificed thereunto, and therefore his wrath was waxen hot againſt the people to haue con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed them.</hi> Yea, it faileth ſo farre that God will
<pb facs="tcp:21800:7"/> be worſhipped by Image<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, as that he will not at all be ſo much as ſerued <hi>BEFORE IMAGES.</hi> For thus ſound forth aloud his owne words. <hi>Yee</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Leuit.</hi> 26. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>ſhall make you no Idols nor grauen Image, neither reare you vp a ſtanding Image,</hi> (or Pillar) <hi>neither ſhall yee ſet vp any Image of ſtone in your Land, to bow down vnto it, or before it.</hi> And therfore before Images we ought not to pray, not to baptize, not to adminiſter the Lords Super. For whether a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hood-winke himſelfe, or no; whether a man ſee the Images, or ſee them not; yet it is all one, and directly againſt the will of God, that any ſhould pray before Images.</p>
               <p>If now it be not lawfull at all for vs to honour and worſhip the Lord Chriſt through and by I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages; then is it much leſſe lawfull for vs to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and worſhip the Saints deceaſſed, as the Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin <hi>Mary, Peter, Wenceſlaus, Rochus, Sebaſtian</hi> &amp; others, by and before the Images. For, beſides that the Saints departed are not to be worſhipped or prayed vnto, neither in regard of themſelues; for it is written: <hi>Thou ſhalt worſhip the Lord thy</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 4. 10.</note> 
                  <hi>God, and him onely ſhalt thou ſerue:</hi> nor yet in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of their being Mediators and Interceſſors: For it is written: <hi>For there is one God, and one Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diator betweene God and Men, euen the Man Christ</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>Ieſus.</hi> Wherefore; <hi>If any man ſinne, wee haue an</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1. <hi>Iohn</hi> 2. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>Aduocate with the Father Ieſus Chriſt the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous: And hee maketh interceſsion for the Saints ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 27.</note> 
                  <hi>to the will of God. For hee is entered into</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 9. 24.</note> 
                  <hi>Heauen it ſelfe, now to appeare in the preſence of</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:21800:7"/> 
                  <hi>God for vs.</hi> And therefore they haue great need to looke well about them and conſider, how they will one day anſwere for it before God, who now ſo much loue Images, as that they honour them with the putting off of the Hat, with kneeling, and with other like Ceremonies. For they belong vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the number of thoſe, of whom the Prophet <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaiah</hi> ſpeaketh in his ſecond Chapter, ſaying: <hi>Their</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſai.</hi> 2. 8, 9.</note> 
                  <hi>Land is full of Idols, they worſhip the worke of their owne hands, that which their owne fingers haue made. There the meane men bow downe, &amp; the great men humble themſelues: This thou wilt not forgiue them.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the third.</head>
               <p>Here hence now it is eaſie to conclude, what <note place="margin">3. That Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates ought to remoue all Images from the Churches, they meane to worſhip God in.</note> then a Chriſtian Magiſtrate is to doe, when for his ſeruing of God he taketh in a Church, which is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleniſhed with Idol-Images? The Lord him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe determines the matter, <hi>Exod.</hi> 34. 13. <hi>Thou ſhalt deſtroy their Altars, breake downe their Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and cut downe their groues.</hi> And <hi>Deut.</hi> 7. 5. <hi>Thus ſhall ye deale with them; Ye ſhall deſtroy their Altars, and breake downe their groues, and burne their gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen Images with fire.</hi> Againe, <hi>Deut.</hi> 12. 3. <hi>You ſhall ouerthrow their Altars, and breake their Pillars, and burne their groues with fire, and you ſhall hewe downe the grauen Images of their gods, and destroy the names of them out of that place.</hi> And 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 7. 3. <hi>Samuel ſpake vnto all the houſe of Iſrael, ſaying: If ye doe returne vnto the Lord with all your hearts, then put away the ſtrange gods, and Aſhtaroth from among</hi>
                  <gap reason="missing" extent="1+ pages">
                     <desc>〈1… pages missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="ground">
               <pb facs="tcp:21800:8"/>
               <head>The firſt ſuppoſed ground is,</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>That God ſpeaketh in the ten Commandements,</hi> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>1</label> 
                  <hi>of the Idol-Images of the Heathen and vnbeleeuing people: Therefore the Commandement of Images, concerneth not at all the Images of Chriſtians vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the new Testament.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Anſwere is: It is falſe, that God in the old <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
                  </label> Teſtament, ſpake onely of the Idols of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then. For the tenne Commandements are Gods e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting vnchangeable will, and extend vnto all people, and euery one in the whole World; as alſo vnto all and euery age and time, both of the olde and new Teſtament. Now as a Thiefe or an Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terer in the new Teſtament, ſinnes as well againſt the ten Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandements, as did a Thiefe and an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulterer in the old Teſtament: euen ſo, whoſoeuer honoureth and worſhippeth Images in the new Teſtament, he ſinneth as wel againſt the ten Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements, as hee who did honour and worſhip Idols in the old Teſtament.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="ground">
               <head>The ſecond ſuppoſed ground.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Yet God himſelfe had in</hi> Salomons <hi>Temple all</hi> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>2</label> 
                  <hi>manner of Images.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I anſwere: It is very true indeed: But there <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
                  </label> were not there any Images at all of any of the Saints departed, as of <hi>Abraham,</hi> of <hi>Iſaack,</hi> and of <hi>Iacob;</hi> there were not any Hiſtoricall commemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratiue Images, of which it is here ſpoken.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="ground">
               <head>The third ſuppoſed ground.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>But yet the common lay people may by Images bee</hi> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>3</label> 
                  <hi>put in mind of many good things: eſpecially by the Crucifix, of the Death and Paſsion of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:21800:8"/>
               <p> I anſwere: It ſtands not in mans will and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
                  </label> that hee inſtitute and ordayne vnto himſelfe, a publike remembrance and commemoration of the benefits of God; but that belongs vnto the Lord God alone to doe, as it is written, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 111. 4 <hi>He hath made his wonderfull workes to be had in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance: the Lord is gracious and full of compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</hi> And euen for this purpoſe hath the Lord God ordayned the preaching of his Goſpell, that by the ſame the benefits of our Lord Chriſt might bee as it were together painted before mens eyes: According as the Apoſtle Saint <hi>Paul</hi> witneſſeth of himſelfe, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3. 1. 2. 5, 6. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> That he had <hi>euident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſet forth Ieſus Chriſt before their eyes;</hi> not by a <hi>Crucifix,</hi> but as himſelfe further acknowledgeth, through <hi>and by the preaching and hearing of faith.</hi> And euen to this end did our Lord Ieſus inſtitute his holy Supper, <hi>that we ſhould celebrate it in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke</hi> 22. 19.</note> 
                  <hi>of him.</hi> For the bread that we breake, <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 24 25, 26.</note> is it not a notable remembrance (I beſeech you) that Ieſus Chriſt endured and ſuffered for vs ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny bitter ſorrowes, and ſuch as neuer man ſuffered <hi>(Conſider, and behold, if euer there were ſorrow like</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lam.</hi> 1. 12.</note> 
                  <hi>my ſorrow)</hi> and at length death it ſelfe, when bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and ſoule were pulled aſunder the one from the other vpon the Croſſe? The Cup of Bleſſing or Thankſgiuing, is it not an excellent remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance, that the bloud of Chriſt Ieſus ranne gent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly out of his body, and was ſhed for our ſinnes? Theſe Remembrancers hath our Lord Chriſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted, and Saint <hi>Paul</hi> hath repeated them. But
<pb facs="tcp:21800:9"/> the Idoll and Imagery Remembrancers hath An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt, euen the Pope inſtituted. Before whoſe being, there was not any Image-remembrancer knowne of in the Church of God. But this was well knowne, <hi>that euery Image was falſhood, Ier.</hi> 10. 14. And that <hi>they be teachers of lyes, Habac.</hi> 2. 18.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="ground">
               <head>The fourth ſuppoſed ground is an Obiection made by Proteſtants:</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>For the abuſe of a thing, a man must not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore</hi> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>4</label> 
                  <hi>caſt away the thing it ſelfe: As a man will not caſt away good Wine, becauſe that ſome abuſe it to drunkenneſſe. Euen ſo we may ſtill retayne Images in Protestant Churches, if we doe but forbeare to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip them and pray vnto them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I anſwere: This rule (A thing is not therefore preſently to be caſt away, becauſe it hath beene a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſed) <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
                  </label> hath not any place or being, in thoſe things which are not of themſelues neceſſary, and yet are withall dangerous. Now all Proteſtants doe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge and confeſſe that Images are not of themſelues at all neceſſary. And that they are dangerous, wee haue here ſeene and beheld with our eyes in this very Church. Therefore Images may not by the foreſaid Rule, bee at all defended or excuſed. Beſides, who knoweth not that the brazen Serpent commanded by God to bee ſet vp <note place="margin">2. <hi>Kin.</hi> 18. 4.</note> and looked vpon, was againe broken downe, when it came to be worſhipped by the people?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="ground">
               <head>The fift ſuppoſed ground.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Why</hi> (may ſome ſay) <hi>thou ſtandest now thy ſelfe</hi> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>5</label> 
                  <hi>in that Pulpit, from whence much Idolatrous mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:21800:9"/> 
                  <hi>hath bin preached. Thou doest celebrate the Lords Supper in that Church, wherein the Papists haue held their Maſſe. Wherefore then is not both Pulpit and Church broken downe together?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I anſwere: We teach not that all that ſhould be <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
                  </label> broken downe, which men haue abuſed, or might abuſe vnto Idolatry. For ſo ſhould Heauen, and all created things bee deſtroyed. But wee teach thus, That all thoſe things which a man may well ſpare, and which are dangerous, and may lightly giue vnto this or that body an occaſion to Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, bee in time remoued and caſt away, agreeably vnto the cleere and plaine Word of God, 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 5. 22. <hi>Be not partaker of other mens ſins: keepe thy ſelfe pure.</hi> Againe <hi>Thou ſhalt not tempt the LORD thy God.</hi> According to this Rule did the godly Prieſts (in the time of magnanimous, heroicall Champion <hi>Iudas Maccabeus)</hi> reforme all, when as the holy Place had bin grieuouſly prophaned by that wicked <hi>Antiochus.</hi> They brake not down the Temple, in which there had beene ſhamefull Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry commited: <hi>but they clenſed, and bare the defiled ſtones into an vncleane place,</hi> as it is written, 1. <hi>Mac.</hi> 4. 42. 43. According to this Rule, our Lord, <hi>Mat.</hi> 21. 12, 13. made reformation at Hieruſalem. For he neither brake downe the Temple, nor yet the Phariſies Pulpit, from whence they taught meerely mens traditions and inuentions. <hi>But he caſt out all them that bought and ſold in the Temple, and ouerthrew the tables of the money changers, and the ſeats of them that ſold Doues; wherby they had made his Houſe of Prayer, a Den of theeues.</hi> The
<gap reason="missing" extent="1+ pages">
                     <desc>〈1… pages missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:21800:10"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>What? Will ye be wiſer then the Ancients? Our</hi> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>8</label> 
                  <hi>fore-fathers had for many hundred yeares agoe, the Images in worth and honour in this place.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I anſwere: Whether in this reſpect wee will bee <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
                  </label> wiſer then the Ancients, I therunto let King <hi>Dauid</hi> anſwere in his 119. <hi>Pſalme,</hi> 100. <hi>v.</hi> where he ſaith: <hi>I vnderstand more then the Ancients, becauſe I keep thy Precepts.</hi> But if a man will enquire of the age of Images amongſt Chriſtians, then it will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare, that afore twelue hundred yeares, afore thirteene hundred yeares, afore fourteene hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred yeares, afore fifteene hundred yeares, afore ſixteene hundred yeares, there was not any I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of God the Father, any Image of God the Sonne, any Image of God the Holy Ghoſt, any Image of any Saint departed, found at all in any of the Chriſtians Churches and Houſes of Prayer. Yea, looke how many Images, how many Altars, how many Challices, how many Maſſing Veſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are yet found amongſt vs; ſo many preſent witneſſes are there, that wee are ſtept aſide from the ancient ſimplicitie: when as they knew not of any Image, of any Altar, of any Challice, of any Maſſing Veſtments. As the ſame is as cleere as the Sun-ſhine, to be ſhewed out of <hi>Iuſtin Martyrs</hi> ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Apologie, out of <hi>Irenaeus, Tertullian, Origen, Cyprian,</hi> and other much eſteemed worthy anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Fathers.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="ground">
               <head>The ninth ſuppoſed ground.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>And if we will haue the Images put downe, then</hi> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>9</label> 
                  <hi>ought they firſt to be put out of mens hearts, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards from before their eyes.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:21800:10"/>
               <p> I anſwere: Thus ſay men here on Earth; and it <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
                  </label> is all earthly humane reaſon. But God that is in Heauen, ſaith farre otherwiſe: <hi>Breake them downe, destroy them, burne them;</hi> that is, put them away from before your eyes, and out of your ſight. And that not without great reaſon. For euen like as a man will not ſee a Thiefe that hee ſteale, and will not ſee an Adulterer that hee breake Wedlocke, with an opinion that Theft and Adultery muſt be firſt ſhewed vnto him out of Gods Word to bee vnlawfull: Euen ſo ſhould not, nor can a Chriſtian Magiſtrate ſee and behold that men rob the Lord of his honour, and vſe alliance with Images; ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Commandement: <hi>Thou ſhalt not make vnto thy ſelfe any Image, thou ſhalt not bow downe vnto it nor worſhip it;</hi> is euen as cleere and euident, as the Commandements: <hi>Thou ſhalt not ſteale: Thou ſhalt not commit Adultery.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="ground">
               <head>The tenth ſuppoſed ground.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>The people are offended at the taking downe, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouing and putting away of Images.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">10. <hi>Obiect.</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>I anſwere: They tooke offence alſo at our Lord Chriſts preching, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 6. Should not Chriſt therfore haue preached? Whoſoeuer doth the will of God, he hath not any need to feare any offence at all to be by him occaſioned and giuen. But whoſoeuer is offended at the full doing of the will of God, hee ſinneth both againſt God, &amp; againſt his Neighbor.</p>
               <p>Out of all which, euery one may well perceiue and vnderſtand, what a number of weighty and perſwaſiue reaſons did together inforce his Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all
<pb facs="tcp:21800:11"/> Maieſtie is not at all any way purpoſed, to compell or grieue any mans conſcience: as alſo hee hath neuer yet done in his own hereditary Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries. For in this reſpect, he holds with the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror <hi>Maximilian</hi> the ſecond, who was wont to ſay: <hi>That Kings commanded and bare Rule ouer their Subiects bodies, but not ouer their Conſciences.</hi> But yet for all this, his Royall Maieſtie will not (as it were not ſitting he ſhould) haue his owne Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence inſnared; and therefore deſireth to ſerue the Lord God, according to that cleere knowledge wherewith God hath enlightned him, and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that his will, which he hath reuealed vnto him. And what that reuealed will of God is, yee haue now alreadie ſufficiently vnderſtood: Name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>He will not be pictured, as alſo hee ought not, nor yet can be pictured.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>He wil not be honored, by, through, or before Images</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>He will, that men breake downe all Images, and wholy depend on him alone with all the heart.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Whoſoeuer therefore now (in the feare of God) truly thinkes on all theſe things, hee will not at all be offended at the remouing, and caſting away of all Images herehence: But hee will much rather, greatly thanke the Lord God, that the publique abhomination and great offence, is in time remoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued and taken away.</p>
               <p>And if yet there ſhould perhaps be any, who hath notwithſtanding ſtill ſome doubt and ſcruple in his minde, let him but pleaſe confidently to
<pb facs="tcp:21800:11"/> come vnto vs: and he ſhall with all loue, mildnes, and well befitting good reſolution bee anſwered, and haue more full information and ſatisfaction giuen vnto him by vs out of Gods Word. For it is our very intent and purpoſe, wholly ſo to labour and indeauour to bring much people vnto ſauing knowledge, as that therby they may rightly come to know, and gladly acknowledge the true <hi>Will</hi> of God, and according to ſuch knowledge, zealouſly and faithfully to ſerue him. Whereunto, the Lord vouchſafe both vnto vs &amp; to you the holy Spirit, who hath promiſed and bound himſelfe to giue it vs, if we call faithfully vpon him for it: euen Ieſus Chriſt the righteous, bleſſed and prayſed, with the Father and the Holy Ghoſt, now &amp; for euer, <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>The Prayer after the Sermon.</head>
               <p>ALmighty, moſt mercifull, moſt gracious, lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing God and Father, we giue thee moſt hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble prayſe and thankes for all thy mercies and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits, which wee vnceſſantly haue receiued, and ſtil do of thy rich goodneſſe; that thou haſt ſo gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly gouerned vs all the whole time of our life long, protected and preſerued vs, and euen hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto haſt kept vs. But eſpecially and aboue all wee thanke thee deare Father, that thou haſt ſuffered vs to liue to ſee the good day, wherin this Church is clenſed and purged from all Idolatry &amp; Images.</p>
               <p>Wee beſeech thee O eternall Lord God, graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly to enlighten their eyes, who yet ſit in the dark<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <gap reason="missing" extent="1+ pages">
                     <desc>〈1… pages missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:21800:12"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:21800:12"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
